Julian D. Hayden Photograph Collection, 1934-1942
University of Arizona Library Special Collections
Julian D. Hayden Photograph Collection 1934-1942
MS 456
Julian D. Hayden
This collection is comprised of personal and professional photographs of Julian D. Hayden. Much of this material relates to his work as an archaeologist, including excavations of Snaketown, Ventana Cave, Pueblo Grande and other excavations. Other photos include Pima Indian ethnographic material, 19th century Arizona ruins and Spanish missions in Arizona and Mexico. Personal photographs include images of Irwin Hayden (Julian D. Hayden’s father,) Emil Haury and other contemporaries of Hayden. There are also some photographs of Julian Hayden’s jewelry work. All images are available in negative format or contact sheets.
.5 linear feet, 35mm photograph negatives and contact sheets
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Notes on Use of Collection
None
Biographical Note
Julian D. Hayden was born in 1911 in Missoula, Montana, raised in Riverside, California and came to Arizona in 1929 where he remained until he passed away in Tucson, March 6, 1998. Julian received an Associate of Arts from Riverside Junior College prior to moving to Pueblo Grande Archaeological Park. Julian spent much of his life promoting and protecting the Sierra Pinacate in northern Sonora, Mexico, although he made significant contributions to Hohokam and southwestern Arizona archaeology.
Julian began his archaeological field experiences when he and his Harvard trained father, Irwin Hayden excavated the Grewe ruin and Compound F at Casa Grande Ruins for the Los Angeles County Museum. Irwin and Julian also worked together at Mesa House in southern Nevada with M.R. Harrington, at Kiet Siel in Northern Arizona and with Harold Gladwin and Emil Haury in 1934-1935 at Snaketown in southern Arizona. Julian supervised much of the work at Mound 29 at Snaketown. It was at Snaketown Julian met his wife, Helen Pendleton. Julian and Helen had two sons and two daughters together.>
While at Pueblo Grande Julian became involved in excavating and taking notes and photographs for the Civilian Conservation Corp (CCC) project, under the direction of Odd Halseth. Julian quickly advanced from student technician to junior foreman. In May 1938, Julian was promoted to senior foreman, much to the surprise of the National Park Service, since Julian had no formal academic training.
From 1936 to 1940 Julian supervised the excavation of hundreds of archaeological features; the CCC crews excavated more than 50 rooms in the area, which remains one of the most systematic excavations of a Hohokam platform mound ever undertaken. Julian’s field notes, sketches and 700+ photographs are featured in numerous publications, including Archaeology of the Pueblo Grande Platform Mound and Surrounding Features, C.E. Downum and T.W. Bostwick, eds., Pueblo Grande Museum Anthropological Papers No. 1, 1994. Julian also published multiple articles about the ancient Southwest and contributed his knowledge to ethnographic studies regarding Tohono O’Odham. He received the Don Crabtree Award for Avocation Archaeology in 1988 and in 1992 was honored by Friends of Pronatura for his lifelong advocation of the Sierra Pinacate region. He also served as president for the Arizona Archaeological and Historical Society.
Organization
This collection is organized into three series.
Series I: Snaketown, The Missions of Northern Mexico, San Xavier and Northern Arizona, circa 1934-1935
Series II: Phoenix, The Missions of Northern Mexico, Gila Pueblo, Blackwater and Santa Rosa, Papagueria, Tucson, Morro Colorado, Pueblo Grande, circa 1936-1942
Series III: Ventana Cave, Papagueria, The Kofas, Yuma, circa 1942
Scope and Content Note
The bulk of this collection is from 1934-1942 (Volumes I, II) and focuses on Julian Hayden’s work as an archaeologist. Sites in the collection include, Snaketown, Ventana Cave and Pueblo Grande. The collection also contains many shots of his travels around the Southwest regions, including Pima Indian ethnographic material, 19th century Arizona ruins and Spanish missions in Arizona and Mexico. Personal photographs include Irwin Hayden (Julian D. Hayden’s father,) Emil Haury and other contemporaries of Hayden. There are also some photographs of Julian Hayden’s jewelry work. The original organizational structure created by Julian Hayden has been left intact.
Haury, Emil W. (Emil Walter); Tohono O'odham Indians--Arizona; Tohono O'odham Indians--Social life and customs; Hohokham; Excavations (Archaeology)--Arizona; Indians of North American--Arizona--Antiquities; Archaeologists--Arizona; Indian baskets--Southwest; Missions--Spanish--United States; Hohokham culture--Arizona--Phoenix; Excavations (Archaeology) -- Arizona -- Phoenix; Architecture -- Mexico -- Hermosillo; Photography—Applied; Tohono O'Odham art; Archaeology—Arizona; Pueblo Grande Archaeological Park (Phoenix, Ariz.); Hohokam culture; Arizona--Antiquities; Ventana Cave (Ariz); Tubutama--Mexico; Phoenix (Ariz.) -- Antiquities; film negatives
Container List
- Series I: Snaketown, The Missions of Northern Mexico, San Xavier and Northern Arizona, 1934-1935
  This series is arranged in order imposed by Hayden.
  - Roll 90; Images of excavation of Snaketown, Hohokam pithouses, Irwin Hayden, Pima Indians playing basketball, Julian Hayden. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Roll 14; includes images of Sacaton burial at Snaketown, Snaketown after heavy rain and the camp at the Snaketown excavations (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Roll 100; includes images of Pima horses, Pima reservation, Camp Snaketown, backfilling of Snaketown at end of excavation (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Roll 101; includes images of Snaketown excavation, and Estrella house Charles Amsden, Irwin Hayden, Shell braclets, Hayden’s jewelry (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Roll 96; includes images of Camp Snaketown, Emil Haury, deep pithouse, Gila Butte, Pima shrines (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Roll 97; includes images of Juan Smith (Pima storyteller), Helen Hayden, Gila River Reservation (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Roll 99; includes images of Pima basketmaking, Pima roundhouse at Snaketown. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Roll 107; includes images of Gila crossing, Pima woodcutters and wagon team, Maricopa Wells, Butterfield Stagecoach Station in ruins, Komatke Pima Reservation, Petroglyphs, Border Station Dowling-Lukeville, 1935. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Roll 93; includes images of San Francisquiito, Sonora, La Gunitas washing gold, Altar (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Roll 30; includes images of Pitiquito, Missions, Tubutama (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Roll J; includes images of Oquitoa, Tumacacori, ruins at Saric, Missions (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Roll 92; includes images of San Xavier (1935), fortifications in Tubac, Guadalupe Mine (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Roll 91; includes images of Sierra Anchas (June 1935), Petrified Forest, John McGregor excavations, Flagstaff AZ (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Roll 98; includes images of Burros at Corn Springs, Quartzite statues of Yuma warrior and Woman on Blythe Road (north of Phoenix) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Roll 18; includes images of Snaketown 1935, canal trenches, Vallecitos Stage Station on Colorado River, Yuma (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Roll 80; images of Gopher snake at Snaketown (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Roll 72; images of backfilling at Snaketown, Krause Lewis, Julian Hayden, Cave in Estrellas with Papago victims of smallpox shrine, Pima shrines (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Roll 94; images of Erik Reed, Round House, Snaketown, Pueblo Grande (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series II: Phoenix, The Missions of Northern Mexico, Gila Pueblo, Blackwater and Santa Rosa, Papagueria, Tucson, Morro Colorado, Pueblo Grande 1936-1942
  - Introductory materials to Volume 2 by Julian Hayden and Roll#69; includes images of Hermosillo cathedral, Hermosillo (1937), badger, Snow at Pueblo Grande (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Roll 58; includes images of Langdon Kihn, Edna Sanderson, most of roll donated to collections at Pueblo Grande (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Roll 82; includes images of Vikita dance ground Quitovac (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Roll 20; includes images of Caborca, Missions, Tubutama, San Ignacio Mission, Oquitoa? (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Roll 21; includes images of Tubutama, Missions, San Ignacio Mission, Oquitoa (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Roll 78; images of Lime kilns (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Roll 1; images include cremation from Pueblo Grande, Blackwater potter and pottery making process, cotton on Pima Reservation (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Roll 16; images include Children’s Shrines of Tohono O’odham Reservation and mesquite wood mortars and stone pestles at Santa Rosa (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Roll 42; images are chronicling the construction of a Pima Round House circa 1938 at Pueblo Grande (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Roll 73; images of San Ignacio, boat building and photos of Guaymas, Mexico, Pancho Ochoas’s jacal, other travels in Mexico (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Roll 106; images include Pueblo Grande, Saguaro National Monument, CCC Camp at Randolph Park, antelope fawns being reared by veterans at Tucson Mountains CCC Camp (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Roll 108; images of the building of the Water Tower at Randolph Park, Fir Building at Saguaro National Monument, Davis Monthan and Cochineal insects (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Roll 77; images of fishing trip in Estero Tastiota region and Opata Indian guide Pancho Ochoa (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Roll 109; images of Morro Colorado fishing trip to Mexico (also featured in Roll 77, Folder 13) and jewelry by Julian Hayden (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Series III: Ventana Cave, Papagueria, The Kofas, Yuma, 1942
  - Roll 52; includes introductory material by Julian Hayden and images from a book of pottery designs (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Roll 51; includes jewelry by Julian Hayden, petroglyphs near and within Ventana Cave, adobe ruins near Santa Rosa (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Roll 55; images of Ventana cave excavations 1942 1942 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Roll 54; images of Santa Rosa, Papagueria, Juan Xavier, Ash Hill trincheras and hand trenching (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Roll 53; images include excavations at Ventana Cave, Wihom-ki, Ventana Butte, Ash Hill trench, prayer balls, Wihom-ki photographs used in the journal publication, The Kiva, in 1977 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Roll 56; images of coyote carcass hung in tree witchcraft? And Javelina for food and Ventana Butte (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Roll 105; images include Kofa views, San Dieguito trail, highway accident photos (including photo of the deceased driver) taken at request of Highway Patrol by Julian Hayden and Gweyneth and Juan Xavier (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Roll 110; images include Yuma Army Air Base, wood gravestone power shovel, demolition explosions (Box 1, Folder 40)